Guide to the James Branch Cabell Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Branch Cabell collection
1912-1971
1927-1954
YCAL MSS 566
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.1
(6 boxes)
The collection contains letters, manuscripts, and printed material related to the life and work of James Branch Cabell. The letters in Series I were written by Cabell to his publishers, literary collaborator, and colleagues; in most cases the folders include carbon copies of responses sent back to Cabell. Writings in Series II are typescripts and proofs of several works, and include correspondence related to their publication, as well as designs by John O'Hara Cosgrave for the cover and end papers of Cabell's work There Were Two Pirates. Series III holds published material about Cabell, including reviews of his work, in the form of clippings, pamphlets, and other ephemera, and portrait photographs by Carl Van Vechten and Foster Studio, Richmond.
Cabell, James Branch, 1879-1958
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
Foster Studio
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was assembled by library staff and was acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded at the folder level in the contents list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Branch Cabell (1879-1958)
James Branch Cabell, American author of works of fiction and non-fiction, including novels, comedies, short stories, essays, poetry, and writings on genealogy. He was a native of Richmond, Virginia, and a graduate of the College of William and Mary.
For a full biography and bibliography of his work, see Cabell's entry in the online Encyclopedia of Virginia at http://www.encyclopediavirginia.org/Cabell_James_Branch_1879-1958 (accessed November 12, 2012).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters, manuscripts, and printed material related to the life and work of James Branch Cabell. The letters in Series I were written by Cabell to his publishers, literary collaborator, and colleagues; in most cases the folders include carbon copies of responses sent back to Cabell. Writings in Series II are typescripts and proofs of several works, and include correspondence related to their publication, as well as designs by John O'Hara Cosgrave for Cabell's work There Were Two Pirates. Series III holds biographical material and published reviews of Cabell's work in the form of clippings, pamphlets, and other ephemera, along with portrait photographs of Cabell by Carl Van Vechten and by the Foster Studio, Richmond.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1958. II. Writings, 1928-1949. III. Printed Material and Photographs, 1912-1971.
Authors, American -- Virginia -- 20th Century -- Archives; Galley proofs; Layouts (printer matter); Page proofs; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Studio portraits -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- Virginia -- 20th Century; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Cabell, James Branch, 1879-1958; Canby, Henry Seidel, 1878-1961; Cosgrave, John O'Hara, II, 1908-1968; Farrar, John Chipman, 1896-1974; Hanna, Alfred Jackson, 1893-; Machen, Arthur, 1863-1947; Swan, Bradford F. (Bradford Fuller); Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Farrar & Rinehart; Foster Studio
- Correspondence, 1918-1951; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Additional correspondence related to Cabell's publications is filed in Series II.
  - Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1926-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of James T. Babb, 1959 and 1961.
  - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1922 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gift of Henry S. Canby, 1953.
  - Farrar, John Chipman, 1927-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of John Chipman Farrar, 1949, 1950, 1955, 1956, and 1958.
    Scope and Contents
    65 letters to Farrar and 1 letter to Margaret Petherbridge Farrar; 3 letters to M. B. Sheffield; 1 letter to J. Kempner; 2 letters from Margaret Freeman Cabell to Farrar; 1 telegram and 3 carbon letters from Farrar to Cabell
    Also in the folder is Farrar's correspondence with David L. Barnett, William Lawton Maner, and Josephine Pinkney regarding Cabell.
  - Farrar & Rinehart, and Rinehart & Company, Inc., 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4-14)
    Gift of Rinehart & Company, Inc., 1949.
    112 letters to Farrar & Rinehart (correspondents include: John Chipman Farrar, Stanley M. Rinehart, Philip Wylie, Adelaide A. Sherer, Marguerite J. Reese and William Raney) with carbon copies of the publishers' replies and letters to and from other publishers and agents
  - Gruener, Gustav, 1922 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Acquired on exchange from the German Literature Collection, 1967.
  - Hanna, Alfred Jackson, 1938-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16-22)
    Purchased on the George B. Alvord Fund and American Studies' funds, 1965.
    154 letters and 4 telegrams to Hanna, with whom Cabell collaborated on The St. Johns for the "Rivers of America" series; 34 letters and 2 telegrams from Hanna to Cabell; and 1 letter to Mrs. Price
  - Kane, Lawrence J., 1922 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Gift of Mrs. Arthur Head, 1948.
  - Machen, Arthur, 1918 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Swan, Bradford F. (Bradford Fuller), 1946 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Gift of Bradford F. Swan, 1949.
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1919-1949 (Box 1, Folder 25a)
    Gift of Mrs. Margaret Waller Freeman Cabell, 1962.
- Writings, 1928-1949; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Writings by Cabell that were published in newspapers appear in folders 45 and 46 in Series III.
  - The Devil's Own Dear Son, typescript, corrected, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    Gift of John Chipman Farrar, 1949.
  - The Jewel Merchants, preface, typescript, corrected; signed by Cabell on May 21, 1948, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Gift of James Branch Cabell, 1948.
  - Let Me Lie, typescript, page proofs, and galleys, corrected, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 29-32)
  - Sonnets From Antan
    Gift of Louis M. Rabinowitz, 1944.
    - Typescripts, corrected and page proofs, corrected, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Includes 5 typescript letters to James R. Wells.
    - Printed version, signed by Cabell, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - There Were Two Pirates
    - Correspondence regarding publishing, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Correspondents include Roger W. Straus, John Chipman Farrar, and Julius Fleischmann.
    - Postcards, some with notes by Cabell regarding various places and objects in Florida and their use as the setting for the story, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Typescript and carbon copy, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    - Sample book pages and designs for cover, end papers, illustrations, etc., by John O'Hara Cosgrave, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - Galley and page proofs, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - The Witch Woman
    - Typescript and page proofs, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Galleys, corrected, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
- Printed Material and Photographs, 1912-1971; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Printed material arranged chronologically, with photographs at the end.
  - Clippings and pamphlets by and about Cabell, 1912-1979 (Box 5, Folder 45-46)
  - Reviews of Cabell's writings, 1921-1961 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - "Figures of Allegory" by Leon Howard; study of James Branch Cabell reprinted from the Sewanee Review, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - The Virginia Author 1819-1969; University of Virginia Library exhibition checklist (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - The Cabellian: A Journal of the Second American Renaissance; vol. 4, no. 1, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "The Map of Philip Borsdale, circa 1679," by Frank Cheney Papé, circa 1928
    General note
    Title within map image: Poictesme; shows the places mentioned in the novels Figures of Earth, Domeni, Jurgen, The High Place, and The Silver Stallion.
    Gift of James T. Babb, 1939.
  - "James Branch Cabell," by Frank Cheney Papé; portrait etching of James Brand Cabell, signed, 1930
    Typscript notation on verso: This is one of the 210 Impressions, of which 200 are for sale, and plate has been destroyed.
  - Portrait photographs by Carl Van Vechten (2) and Foster Studio, Richmond, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Oversize, 0.13; (1 box)
  - In Series II: There Were Two Pirates, designs for cover, end papers, illustrations, etc., by John O'Hara Cosgrave, 1946 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 52)
  - In Series III: "The Map of Philip Borsdale, circa 1679," by Frank Cheney Papé, circa 1928 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 53)
  - In Series III: "James Branch Cabell," by Frank Cheney Papé; portrait etching of James Brand Cabell, signed, 1930 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 54)